Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 14 -- Materials held at the University of Pennsylvania 1705-1788 Mss.B.F85inventory14
American Philosophical Society
- Correspondence (University of Pennsylvania), 1758-1788
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Deane, Silas. Paris
    Explaining the matter of his expenses; wishes to demonstrate the rectitude of his conduct, and the justice of his demands on Congress; meets some of the accusations made.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 3; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Perregaux, -----. Paris
    Sending him a letter, entrusted to his care.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 8; A.L.S. 3p.; O'Donnoghue, -----. Bruges
    Desires information concerning a certain O'Donnoghue, born in Philadelphia; said to be a Catholic; question concerning the social and political standing of the American O'Donnoghues.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Foster March Penny and requesting a pass to London for him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Petry, -----. Paris
    Expressing his belief that his brother, who has gone to fight in America, will be worthy of Dr. Franklin's letters of recommendation.
  - Appendix, 1781 October 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Money furnished American prisoners; letter from John Adams stating that no more prisoners must be sent to Amsterdam; question of where to send them. Enclosing a letter from Tho[ma]s Beer [2p.] who is destitute and wishes to emigrate to Ameirica.
  - Appendix, 1781 October 19; L.S. 2p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    Thinks it is a mistake for American prisoners who have escaped from the British, to come to Holland; cites case of Mr. [Thomas] Beer.
  - Appendix, 1781 October 22; L.S. 2p.; Gourlade and Moylan. L'Orient
    Question of drawing on Dr. Franklin for the payment of certain bills.
  - Appendix, 1781 October 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Virth, Madame. Hesdin
    Her husband embarks for America, under the orders of Commodore [Alexander] Gillon; the Commodore's promise to send her 60 livres per month; no money has been received; appeal to Dr. Franklin for aid.
  - Appendix, 1781 October 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Hancock, John. Boston
    Introducing Mr. William Knox, brother of General [Henry] Knox.
  - Appendix, 1781 November 2; A.L.S. 3p.; de Castelle, Le Grand. St. Omer
    Desiring Dr. Franklin's advice as to removing his friend, Col. George Mercer of America, who is ill in a French inn; supposes that an order from Congress is necessary.
  - Appendix, 1781 November 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Madier, -----. Beaucaire
    Offering to send goods to the United States, to be sold at the same price as in Francer encloses a memoir on the subject [3p.].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 November 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Guen, Charles. Morlaix
    Appointed the agent of L'Heritier, Huigen and Co., to collect damages from the United States for the sale of the cargo of the Swedish ship,"Victory," captured by the "Alliance"; encloses copy of his appointment [2p.].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 November 7; 1p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Resolution, directing the Secretary of Foreign Affairs to prepare a sketch of emblems of the United States—French Alliance to be inscribed upon the marble column at York [Town]. Attested copy S. Lewis R. Morris, Sec[retar]y.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 November 9; L.S. 1p.; Amelunxen ?, Madame Myron. Herzebrock
    Begs him to forward the enclosed letter to her brother, who is fighting under [Gen.] Washington; if he is dead, wishes to know it in order to settle affairs of importance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 November 11; A.L.S. 2p.; de la Chambre, Le Chevalier. Caen
    Acknowledging his letter of October 29, confirming the writer's good opinion of M. [Stephen] Gregory, Lieutenant of the United States Marines.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 November 12; L.S. 2p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    Departure of the "South Carolina," from Corunna on October 17th; Capt. [William] Jackson and Mr. [John] Trumbull gone to America. The goods for the American army still at Amsterdam; desires to know if a part had better be sold to pay the freight on the remainder; the soldiers will need them during the winter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 November 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Knox, William. On board "L'Engageante," Groia
    Sends a letter from George Hancock and one from John Temple, also American newspapers with account of [Lord] Cornwallis's surrender.
  - Appendix, 1781 November 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Mr. [Thomas] Barclay. Congratulations on the late glorious news.
  - Appendix, 1781 November 23; D. 2p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Resolutions concerning the Marquis de la Fayette's visit to France.
  - Appendix, 1781 November 26; L.S. 11p.; Livingston, Robert R. Philadelphia
    Recommending a further loan from France and the maintaining of a French fleet on the American coast. Desiring to know if any of Mr. [Silas] Deane's letters to persons in America have been intercepted and published in Europe.
    (In quadruplicate.)
    Printed in Diplom. Corresp. of the Am. Rev., Wharton, V, 4.
  - Appendix, 1781 November 27; L.S. 2p.; Morris, Robert. Philadelphia
    Instructions to Capt. John Barry, of the frigate "Alliance," concerning his future movements.
  - Appendix, 1781 November 27; A.L.S. Geo[rge] Bond, Dep[ut]y Sec[retar]y. 1p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Resolutions empowering Mr. [Robert] Morris to take into his hands all monies belonging to the United States.
  - Appendix, 1781 November 23, 27, December 3; D.S. Peter S. Du Ponceau, Sec[retar]y. 3p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Resolutions allowing Marquis de la Fayette to return to France, appointing him American Agent there, and placing the European loan under the direction of Mr. [Robert] Morris.
  - Appendix, 1781 December 3; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Resolution empowering Mr. [Robert] Morris to dispose of all monies according to the Acts and Resolutions of Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Bache, Richard. Philadelphia
    Mr. [Silas] Deane's letters have ruined him in the opinion of his countrymen; some suspicion cast upon Dr. [Edward] Bancroft.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 4; L.S. 2p.; Morris, Robert. Office of Finance
    Mr. [John] Ross's bills should be paid, not sent back protested. Payments made to M. [Ferdinand] Grand and to Mr. [William] Bingham.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Cramer, Catherine de Wesselow
    Congratulating him upon the success of the American arms in Virginia. News of his grandson [Benjamin Franklin Bache]; question of his studies; gives him the same degree of care accorded to her own children. Concerning a position for Madame [Dorcas] Montgomery.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 10; 3p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Resolution directing the States to fill their quotas in troops by a certain date. Extract from the Minutes. S. Geo[rge] Bond, Dep[ut]y Sec[retar]y. Copy attested by L[ewis] R. Morris, Sec[retar]y.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 16; L.S. 3p.; Livingston, Robert R. Philadelphia
    Wilmington, a center of Toryism, evacuated, leaving the North Carolina tories to the mercy or resentment of their countrymen. Desiring a sketch for a memorial pillar to be erected at Yorktown. Encloses an ordinance of Congress prohibiting the importation of all British goods not captured.
    (In duplicate and triplicate.)
    Printed in Diplom. Corresp. of the Am. Rev., Wharton, V, 53.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 December 22; A.L.S. 3p.; de Bres, Chevalier. Nice
    Soliciting his aid for four young men who wish to enter the American Army; unknown to Dr. Franklin; gives references.
  - Appendix, 1781 December 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Jaume, Guillaume. Lyons
    Desires him to send his grandson [Benjamin Franklin Bache] to a Catholic Academy in which he is interested; describes the curriculum; Protestants frequently place their children in this school.
  - Appendix, 1781 December 24; L.S. 1p.; de Preuille, Madame Bouroyan. St. Martin
    Begging that the enclosed letters may be forwarded to her grandson at Boston.
  - Appendix, A.L.S. 2p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, -----
    Affairs of M. Coder Purchase of canvas. A consulship in Normandy without pay for M. Grégoire. Exchange of the writer's nephew, taken prisoner by the English. Encloses a note for Mr. [John] Adams and a letter for M. [Mottin] de la Balme.
  - Appendix, 1781; A.L.S. 1p.; Gébelin, Antoine Court de
    Thanking him for accepting an invitation to a meeting of the Lodge [des Neuf Soeurs].
  - Appendix, A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Sending an extract from a letter from Mr. [Jonathan] Williams, [Jr.], of Nantes, concerning 6 per cent Congressional Bonds payable in 1781, and deposited with him.
  - Appendix, [Circa 1781.]; A.L.S. 1p.; Morellet, abbé
    Sending him a part of his work upon the American Colonies. Leaves it to Dr. Franklin to say whether or not it shall be published.
  - Appendix, A.L.S. 1p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Paris
    Encloses speeches of Mr. [Charles James] Fox. The London paper honored the writer by recording that he breakfasted with Mr. [Henry] Laurens. Enclosing resolutions of the Volunteer Corps, showing their contempt for the treachery of Mr. [Francis] Dobbs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Circa 1781; A.L.S. 1p.; Nogaret, François-Félix
    Regretting that the missed his visit; accepts his invitation for Thursday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781; L.S. 3p.; Oster, Madame
    Desires his aid in finding and rejoining her husband.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Circa 1781.]; Printed N. S. De Séqueville. 1p.; The Secretary to the King. Paris
    Announcement that the King will not see the Ambassadors on the day appointed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Printed N.S. De Séqueville. 1p.; The Secretary to the King. Paris
    Notice to meet Comte de Vergennes, in order to discuss affairs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 February 1; A.L.S. 23p.; Deane, Silas. Ghent
    A history of his past and present situation; question of his private letters being intercepted, in which he had criticized America's policy; defends his own statements; accuses Dr. Franklin of having used greater freedom in his political writings; question of his accounts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 March 9; L.S. 1p.; Livingston, Robert R. Philadelphia
    Enclosing a letter, in cipher, from Robert Morris.
    Printed in Diplom. Corresp. of the Am. Rev., Wharton, V, 232.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 March 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Jackson, William. Calais
    His attachment to the United States has cost him his fortune; formerly conductor of the Public Ledger; in 1777, communicated to Mr. [William] Carmichael intelligence of the secret correspondence between [Comte de] Maurepas and Lord Mansfield. Is now visiting the Duchess of Kingston [Elizabeth Chudleigh], and may accompany her to the Court of St. Petersburg; desires to be of service to the United States.
  - Appendix, 1782 March 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Rousseaux, Jean
    Refers to his two former letters and begs that his petition may be answered, and if possible, granted.
  - Appendix, 1782 April 8; L.S. 8p.; Morris, Robert. Office of Finance
    Money needed for purchasing supplies for the States; a further sum will have to be drawn on France; if necessary all French advances could be repaid at the end of the year; for this he pledges his personal honor.
    (In cipher, with translation.)
  - Appendix, 1782 April 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Hilliard d’Auberteuil, Michel-René. Paris
    Forwarding proof sheets and requesting the return of those previously sent.
  - Appendix, 1782 April 13; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Announcing the date of his departure.
  - Appendix, 1782 April 17; L.S. 4p.; Morris, Robert. Philadelphia
    Two million livres will need to be drawn on France; the Dutch loan will provide in part for the payment.
    (In cipher, untranslated.)
  - Appendix, 1782 April 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Wright, John. London
    Introducing William Rawle, son of the late Francis Rawle, of Philadelphia. Failure of their old friends Brown, Collinson and Tritton; hopes Dr. Franklin loses nothing thereby. The new Ministry apparently determined to proceed on true Constitutional principles.
  - Appendix, 1782 April 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Thun, Ulrich, baron de. Paris
    Announcing the embezzlement, followed by the flight of the Ducal Cashier of Wurtemberg; reported as intending to secure Dr. Franklin's aid in passing to America; encloses a description of the offender, with a request for his apprehenson; a similar letter sent to the Chief of Police at Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 1; A.L.S. 4p.; Hewson, Mrs Mary. Kensigton
    News of her son; her girl greatly pleased with Dr. Franklin's denunciation of stays. Her loss by the failure of Collinson's house. Description of a travelling coach fitted with [Thomas] Viny's wheels, if he wishes to buy one.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Imbault, -----. Orléans
    Desiring information as to the best method of reaching America; has determined to emigrate there with his family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Roux, C.J. Versailles
    Sends a book written by a man who saved his wife's life; he will find it full of valuable knowledge.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 7; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Orders concerning the exchange of prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Jay, John. Madrid
    Dr. Franklin's letters of the 22d and 23d ult. have determined him to come to Paris; the French Ambassador not averse to the step; the Count de Florida Blanca will refer the instructions intended for M. Del Campo to the Count d'Aranda at Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Hilliard d’Auberteuil, Michel-René. Paris
    Sending the proof of his new work [Essais historiques et politiques sur les Anglo-Américains]; his poor health has retarded the printing and prevented him paying his respects to Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 10; 6p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Portsmouth, New Hampshire
    Concerning the Dutch ship "Berkenbos(ch)"; explains his actions regarding her. Prize-money still due the crew of the "Bon Homme Richard."
  - Appendix, 1782 May 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Hilliard d’Auberteuil, Michel-René. Paris
    Sends proof-sheets; hopes that the third part of his work will be completed the following week.
  - Appendix, 1782 May 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Foulke, John. Paris
    Encloses Dr. Franklin's letter upon the insect Ephemera; copied it for Miss [Bethia] Alexander.
  - Appendix, 1782 May 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Report that America has declared war against Portugal that six rich Brazil ships have been captured and that Capt. [John] Paul Jones is the hero; all Portuguese Captains at Bordeaux ordered to await instructions at Lisbon; the insurance of Portugal vessels raised.
  - Appendix, 1782 May 16; L.S. 1p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Paid for the passage to America of William Stevenson and George Cabot, who had been prisoners in England.
  - Appendix, 1782 May 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Hilliard d’Auberteuil, Michel-René. Paris
    Asking the immediate return of the proof-sheets; sends more.
  - Appendix, 1782 May 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Hilliard d’Auberteuil, Michel-René. Paris
    Sending proof-sheets. Returning the copy of the Acts of Congress. Much talk of peace; desire it greatly.
  - Appendix, 1782 May 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Price, Richard. Newington Green
    Introducing Messrs. Milford and Brown. Rejoices over the change of Ministry in England; thinks the prospect of peace improved thereby.
  - Appendix, 1782 May 22; L.S. 5p.; Livingston, Robert R. Philadelphia
    Joy in America over the birth of the Dauphin. Firmness of the United States unshaken by England's conciliatory attitude. The people disappointed at the French fleet's departure the year before at a time when a month's stay would have releived either New York of Charleston. Question of an Exchange of Prisoners.
    Printed in Diplom. Corresp. of the Am. Rev. Wharton, V, 434.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 23; L.S. 3p.; Morris, Robert. Office of Finance
    Gives his reasons for requesting that none of the six millions appropriated by the French for the use of the United States, be applied to the payment of M. [Pierre Augustin caron de] Beaumarchais's claim.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1782.] May 24; A.L.S. 4p.; Nogaret, François-Félix
    Concerning his wife's desire to have painted a medallion of Dr. Franklin, with permission to wear it pendant from her collar.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Barclay, David. London
    Sending by Baron Dimsdale two attempts on the character of their late valuable friend, Dr. [John] Fothergill.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 28; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 2p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Resolution relative to settling the accounts of the public servants of the United States, in Europe.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 30; A.L.S. 3p.; Merville, A-----en. Abbeville
    Sends a sample of his wonderful curative powder; heals wounds readily and keeps the ranks of an army from being depleted.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 May 30; A.L.S. 9p.; Livingston, Robert R. Philadelphia
    Question of the prize-money due Capt. [John] Paul Jones and his men. Powers injured by America should never appeal to France. The hanging of Capt. Huddy by the the British and retaliation by Gen. Washington. High opinion of the Marquis de la Fayette.
    Printed in Diplom. Corresp. of the Am. Rev., Wharton, V, 461.
  - Appendix, [1782. May.]; A.L.S. 2p.; Nogaret, François-Félix
    Desiring Dr. Franklin to support his application for the position of reader to the Due de Berry; enclosing a copy of a letter from M. Amelot to the Marquis de Sérent endorsing his request [1p.].
  - Appendix, 1782 June 4; A.L.S. 1p.; fils, Jaubert. Dunkirk
    Asking for a letter of marque against Portugal.
  - Appendix, 1782 June 6; L.S. 1p.; Fizeaux, Grand and Co. Amsterdam
    Have drawn on him for money owed by Mr. John Adams, crediting the same to the account of the United States.
  - Appendix, 1782 June 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Alexander, Miss Bethia.
    Owing to the plague all the plans of the Philosophical Society of Toulouse are abandoned; Dr. Franklin therefore relieved from his part in the ceremonies. Reminds him of his promise to call on the Comtesse de la Marck.
  - Appendix, 1782 June 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Hilliard d’Auberteuil, Michel-René. Paris
    Acknowledging his corrections of American Geographical names; thanking him for information concerning Chadd's [Ford].
  - Appendix, 1782 June 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Perier, Alard Dt. Grenoble
    Desires to emigrate to America, with his eight children; believes the absence of luxury there would enable him to live more cheaply than in France; asks for letters of introduction.
  - Appendix, 1782 June 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Favi, Francesco
    Sends a book and a letter from M. Ingen Housz; will take charge of any reply.
  - Appendix, 1782 June 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Hilliard d’Auberteuil, Michel-René. Paris
    Sends proof-sheers; desires their return as soon as possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 18; L.S. 1p.; Van den Yver and Co. Paris
    Desiring letters of recommendation for Henri van Eupen, merchant at Antwerp, who is about to send a vessel to Philadelphia, under the Imperial flag.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 21; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Beaumarchais, Pierre-Augustin Caron de
    Concerning a letter received from [Le Ray] de Chaumont relative to Mr. [Augustin?] Morice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Mr. Tardy, of his counting house, who can give Dr. Franklin full information of affairs at Nantes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 23; L.S. 3p.; Livingston, Robert R. Philadelphia
    The people determined to make no peace in which their alliance with France is not included. Concerning the pension of [Lieut. Col. Louis] Tousard. Case of the brigantine, "Ersten." Question of Dr. Franklin's expenses.
    Printed in Diplom. Corresp. of the Am. Rev., Wharton, V, 501.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Priestley, Joseph. Birmingham
    Having at last got sunshine, is prosecuting his experiments; these are inconsistent with M. [Antoine Laurent] Lavoisier's supposition that there is no such thing as phlogiston. Is sorry that peace is so long delayed and hopes soon to see Dr. Franklin in England.
    (Fac-simile by American Photo-Lithographic Co., N. Y., in duplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Hilliard d’Auberteuil, Michel-René. Paris
    Delighted with his approbation of his Remarks on the Treaties between the United States and France; these same observations severely condemned by the Department of Foreign Affairs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 June 25; L.S. 3p.; B. Gannan and Zoon. Ostend
    Offering to carry to Philadelphia, despatches, good or other effects.
    A.E. by Dr. Franklin. "Refused."
  - Appendix, 1782 June 27; L.S. 2p.; Poreau and Co. Dunkirk
    Reminding him of his promise to secure the exchange of Capt. Christopher Codner, an American, who had suffered much in English prisons.
  - Appendix, 1782 June 29; A.L.S. 1p.; de Klinglin, L'Abbé. Paris
    Desiring a letter of recommendation for a merchant named La Coste, who is going to Philadelphia.
  - Appendix, Circa 1782; A.L.S. 3p.; Alexander, Miss Bethia.
    Announcing a party of people who will wait upon him at Passy.
  - Appendix, 1782 July 4; L.S 1p.; de La Coste, Madame. Paris
    Thanking Dr. Franklin for the leter he wrote in her husband's behalf.
  - Appendix, 1782 July 5; L.S. 1p.; Livingston, Robert R. Philadelphia
    Transmitting a letter from Congress to the King of France, and a resolution [1p.] on the subject of Mr. William Lee's demands.
    Printed in Diplom. Coresp. of the Am. Rev., Wharton, V, 595.
  - Appendix., 1782 July 7; L.S. 3p.; Bũyck, Pierre. Gand
    Enclosing a letter for Mr. [Henry] Laurens. Has a number of bills on Tho[ma]s Barelay and Commodore [Alexander] Gillon, for goods furnished in Holland for the United States; question of their payment.
  - Appendix, 1782 July 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    Introducing Mr. Benjamin Savage, a young Jewish Tory from South Carolina; lacks nothing except conversion by Franklin.
  - Appendix, 1782 July 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Priestley, Joseph. Birmingham
    Introducing an English traveller. Late experiments interrupted by cloudy weather; the political sky also overcast.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 July 12; A.L.S. 2p.; d'Auzouer, Madame Carroll. Paris
    Sending a letter to be forwarded to Mr. [Charles] Carroll.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 July 15; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Sir William Jones and Mr. John Paradise. Paris
    Reminding him of the letter he promised them; hope to pay their respects to him upon their return from America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 July 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Beauquesne, ----- de. Paris
    Account of his imprisonment by the English, and subsequent shipwreck; has in his care a fifteen year old daughter; begs for aid.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 July 19; A.L.S. 4p.; Hewson, Mrs. Mary. Kensington
    Introducing Dr. [John] Shuttleworth. Account of the struggle to support herself made by Mrs. Wilkes; chance of an opening for her to teach English in France. Acknowledging the book he sent her; praises Madame de Genlis but detests her sophistry, especially with regard to suckling and stays; delighted with Madame de Forbach's little piece.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1782 July 21; L.S. 1p.; Durival, Jean. Versailles
    Desiring his seal in order to affix it to the Convention agreed upon between him and Comte de Vergennes on July 16th.